Did you ever wonder if certain foods
have a direct effect on your health?
Well, I’m here to
solve that mystery
since you are
the foods you eat.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at why it’s so hard
to outrun a bad diet.
When trying to lose weight,
which is more important:
diet or exercise?
A national survey found that
a "vast majority" of Americans
trying to control their weight
believed that food
and beverage consumption
and physical activity
were equally important.
Seven out of ten
went with equally important,
about two out of ten thought
exercise was more important,
and only about one
out of ten chose diet.
The vast majority of Americans
are wrong.
It's easy to understand
how people might think
diet and exercise
play equal roles.
After all,
our weight is determined
by the balance of calories in
and calories out.
What people may not understand
about this
energy balance equation
is we have much more power
over the "calories in" side.
In fact, on a day-to-day basis
we have full control,
we could choose
to eat zero calories
or 10,000 calories.
But most of the "calories out"
tend to be outside
of our control.
Unlike wild animals
who tend to burn
most of their calories
on activity,
about 60 percent
of our daily calories
are used up
just to keep us alive,
what's called our resting,
or basal, metabolic rate,
thanks in part
to our energy-intensive brains.
Even if you stayed in bed
all day,
you'd still burn
more than 1,000 calories
just to fuel the basics
like thinking, breathing,
keeping your heart pumping.
In contrast,
even most "active" people
accrue less than two hours
of exercise a week,
which may average out
to be less than 100 calories
burned off each day.
That's only about 5 percent
of the total
daily energy expenditure,
the "calories out" side
of the equation.
So, the 2,000 calories we may
take in every day from our diet
can exert 20 times
more influence than exercise
over our weight destiny.
Most people believe that
exercise is "very effective"
as a way to lose weight,
but this has been
referred to as a myth
in the scientific literature.
In fact, it's been labeled
one of the most common
misconceptions
in the field of obesity.
Yet virtually all
formal weight-loss guidelines
include some sort of physical
activity recommendation.
Can you outrun a bad diet?
Let's see what the science says.
Population studies
have certainly found
strong correlations between
physical inactivity and obesity.
But does a sedentary lifestyle
lead to obesity,
or does obesity lead
to a sedentary lifestyle?
It probably works a little bit
in both directions.
To prove cause and effect,
and also quantify
the relationship,
you really have to put it
to the test.
Dozens of randomized
controlled trials
involving thousands
of participants
have been published
on the effects of exercise
on weight loss.
Physical activity was not found
to be an effective strategy.
For example,
if you look at the studies
that tried using exercise alone
to induce weight loss,
over an average
of about five months,
people only lost
about three pounds.
When you put
all the studies together,
it looks like it took
around six weeks of exercising
to get people
to lose a single pound.
That was exercise alone, though.
What about as an adjunct
to diet?
If you randomize people
into a diet
and exercise intervention
versus just the diet alone,
the added exercise group
does do better,
but the difference
in weight loss
only averaged about two pounds.
The studies lasted
between 3 and 12 months,
and all of that
extra prescribed exercise
only seemed to translate
into a few pounds.
The two-pound difference
was statistically significant,
which means we're pretty sure
it was a real effect,
but losing two pounds
over a year's time
can hardly be considered
clinically significant.
As a general rule,
researchers like to see
at least a five-
or six-pound drop.
In a meta-analysis of 18
randomized controlled trials
lasting a minimum
of six months,
the diet-plus-exercise group
failed to significantly beat out
the diet-only group at all.
There appeared to be
no long-term benefit
to encouraging people
to add exercise
to their weight-loss regimen.
What is going on?
Maybe exercise is just better
at preventing people
from regaining weight.
No.
The vast majority
of randomized controlled trials
examining
weight-loss maintenance
also failed to show
an exercise benefit.
Part of the problem
is compliance.
It's one thing
to tell people
to adhere
to an exercise regimen;
it's another thing for them
to actually do it.
When the same randomized
controlled trials
were re-analyzed
to exclude people
who flouted the instructions,
and analysis was limited
to just those
who actually put in
the time and sweat,
a clear advantage
to exercise emerges.
Exercise only works
if you actually do it,
though one reason people
may become rapidly disillusioned
with their new gym membership
is their gross overestimation
of the capacity of exercise
to burn off extra calories.
A slice of pizza
has about 300 calories.
That converts into an hour
of brisk walking per slice,
an hour a slice!
How many kids
are jogging two hours a day
to burn off their happy meals?
Who's got time to climb
50 flights of stairs
to take care of the calories
in just one Oreo cookie?
That's one of the reasons
that what we put in our mouths
is most important.
Public health researchers
have been experimenting
with including labeling
on junk food.
Still want that Toblerone
if it means you have to walk
two hours?
Or cookies
you'd have to skip rope
for 81 minutes for?
I think I'd run an hour
just to avoid having to eat
shrimp-flavored potato chips.
Labeling fast food menus
with little pictograms
of exercising stick figures
was found to help nudge people
towards lower calorie options.
Seeing that the decision
to supersize your fries
would mean walking
an extra three miles that day
or that choosing
the chicken salad
over the garden salad
could mean having to run
nearly three miles,
people are more likely
to make the healthier choice.
In our next story,
we look how calories burned
don’t necessarily equal calories lost.
Most overweight individuals
evidently tend
to choose exercise
as their first approach
to weight loss.
When unrealistic hopes
clash with reality,
the disappointment
may lead to an abandonment
of weight-loss efforts
altogether
as an exercise in futility,
no pun intended.
Our false expectations may also
give us license to overeat.
Our pie-in-the-sky notions
about the power of exercise
may just be used to justify
an extra slice of pie
right here on earth.
Some researchers warn
that labeling menus
with calorie equivalents
of exercise
could be counterproductive,
backfiring if people
rationalize their indulgences
after a workout.
This concern has actually been
put to the test.
Exercise psychologists
took a group men and women,
put them on a stationary bike,
and had them cycle
until they burned
either 50 calories
or more than 250 calories.
Unbeknownst to them,
the researchers
manipulated the machines
to give false readouts,
such that in actuality
both groups burned
the same number of calories.
They just thought
they burned more or less.
Then, they were offered a meal
10 minutes later,
ostensibly to measure
the "effects of exercise
on taste perception,"
but the real purpose
was to covertly measure
how much people ate.
Those who falsely believed
they had burned off
more calories
did seem to demonstrate
a greater "license to eat,"
ending up eating
significantly more calories,
mostly in the form
of chocolate chip cookies.
After a workout,
people may be tempted
to treat themselves
for their sweaty sacrifice.
To prevent
this kneejerk reaction
from undermining our efforts,
we should strive to make
exercise less of a chore.
In a paper entitled
"Is it fun or exercise?
The framing of physical activity
biases subsequent snacking,"
a study is described in which
individuals were randomized
to the same amount
of physical activity
but just described differently.
Half were told they were going
on a "scenic walk,"
and the other half were told
they were going on
an "exercise walk."
Afterwards,
researchers covertly measured
how much dessert everyone took
at a subsequent meal.
Those in the
movement-as-exercise group
reportedly served themselves
about 35 percent more
chocolate pudding
than the movement-as-fun group.
This is all the more reason
to choose activities
that are enjoyable,
such as walking with friends
or while listening to music,
or watching a video
on the treadmill.
Reframing exercise as play
rather than work
may not only make
for a more sustainable regimen
but may make us less likely
to consciously
or unconsciously feel the need
to later reward ourselves
at the buffet line.
Even just thinking
about exercise
may compel people
to eat more food.
Those randomized to simply read
about physical activity
went on to serve themselves
nearly 60 percent more M&Ms
than those
in the control group,
adding up to hundreds
of extra calories.
The researchers concluded:
"simply imagining exercise
leads participants to serve
themselves more food."
Expending energy
through exercise
may not just psychologically
predispose us to eat more
but may physiologically
make us hungrier.
We evolved in the context
of scarcity,
so our body
places great value
on rapidly replenishing
lost fat stores.
This helps explain why
the average weight loss
with exercise training
is only 30 percent
of that predicted
based on the number
of extra calories burned.
Calories in
versus calories out
can be complicated
by the fact
that changes on one side
of the equation can affect the other side.
In other words,
we can work up an appetite.
Carefully controlled studies
show that caloric intake
tends to rise over time
to match any increase
in caloric expenditure,
making significant weight loss
through exercise alone
remarkably difficult.
This doesn't happen
over a day or two.
After a workout,
there may not be
an immediate increase in hunger,
but averaged over the week
or weeks,
our appetite does tend
to increase to balance out
most of the extra calories
we've been burning.
This calorie compensation
isn't perfect, though,
so we can end up
with a net loss in body fat,
particularly at
higher exercise levels.
So, the secret to weight loss
through exercise
may be sheer volume,
at least 300 minutes a week
to achieve
appreciable fat loss.
This regulation of our appetite
through activity
works in both directions.
Just as there exists
a higher level of exercise
where we can start to outpace
our appetite and lose weight,
there's a lower level
of exercise
where our body
loses the ability
to sufficiently downgrade
our appetite,
and we gain weight.
This sedentary zone
where our appetite
becomes uncoupled
from our activity level
appears to start
at around 7,100 steps a day.
So, let's say you start out
as a really active person,
chowing down on
nearly 2,900 calories a day,
and, for whatever reason,
have to cut back on exercise.
You'd think you'd gain
a lot of weight,
but you're surprised
that you don't.
Basically, no increased odds
of gaining significant body fat.
With your drop in exercise came
an inadvertent drop in appetite.
But there's a limit to how far
our appetite can drop.
Once you cross that threshold,
once you dip below logging
at least 7,100 steps or so
a day on your pedometer,
your appetite doesn't slow
much further to match,
and the pounds can start
to pile on.
Your body tries
to keep your weight steady
by adjusting your appetite,
but we just weren't designed
to handle such extreme
low levels of movement
that sadly characterizes
most of the U.S. population.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.